And here's the answer: the answer is technology. Now, I know, I know -- yeah, yeah, yeah, technology, automation screws people, blah blah -- that's not what I mean. I'm not talking about the kind of technology that has enveloped our lives, and that people come to TED to hear about. I'm not talking about the technology of things, profound though that is. I'm talking about another technology. I'm talking about the technology of ideas. I call it, "idea technology" -- how clever of me. (Laughter) In addition to creating things, science creates ideas. Science creates ways of understanding. And in the social sciences, the ways of understanding that get created are ways of understanding ourselves. And they have an enormous influence on how we think, what we aspire to, and how we act. If you think your poverty is God's will, you pray. If you think your poverty is the result of your own inadequacy, you shrink into despair. And if you think your poverty is the result of oppression and domination, then you rise up in revolt. Whether your response to poverty is resignation or revolution, depends on how you understand the sources of your poverty. This is the role that ideas play in shaping us as human beings, and this is why idea technology may be the most profoundly important technology that science gives us. And there's something special about idea technology, that makes it different from the technology of things. With things, if the technology sucks, it just vanishes, right?
Y esta es la respuesta: la respuesta es la tecnología. Ya sé, ya sé... sí, sí, tecnología, la automatización jode a la gente, bla, bla; no me refiero a eso. No hablo del tipo de tecnología que ha permeado nuestras vidas, y de la que la gente va a TED a oír. No hablo de la tecnología de las cosas, por muy fundamental que sea. Hablo de otra tecnología, de la tecnología de las ideas. La llamo "tecnología de las ideas"... qué perspicaz de mi parte. (Risas) Además de crear cosas, la ciencia crea ideas. La ciencia crea formas de comprensión, y en las ciencias sociales, las formas de comprensión que se van creando son las formas de entendernos a nosotros mismos. Y tienen una enorme influencia en cómo pensamos, a lo que aspiramos y cómo actuamos. Si creen que su pobreza es la voluntad de Dios, rezarán. Si creen que su pobreza es resultado de su propia incompetencia, caerán en desesperación. Si creen que su pobreza es resultado de la opresión y la dominación, se levantarán en revolución. Que su respuesta a la pobreza sea resignación o revolución, depende de su entendimiento de las causas de su pobreza. Este es el rol que juegan las ideas en formarnos como seres humanos y por eso la tecnología de las ideas quizá sea la tecnología cabalmente más importante que la ciencia nos da. Hay algo especial en la tecnología de las ideas que la diferencia de la tecnología de las cosas. Con las cosas, si la tecnología es mala, entonces sólo desaparece, ¿cierto?
Bad technology disappears. With ideas -- false ideas about human beings will not go away if people believe that they're true. Because if people believe that they're true, they create ways of living and institutions that are consistent with these very false ideas. And that's how the industrial revolution created a factory system in which there was really nothing you could possibly get out of your day's work, except for the pay at the end of the day. Because the father -- one of the fathers of the Industrial Revolution, Adam Smith -- was convinced that human beings were by their very natures lazy, and wouldn't do anything unless you made it worth their while, and the way you made it worth their while was by incentivizing, by giving them rewards. That was the only reason anyone ever did anything. So we created a factory system consistent with that false view of human nature. But once that system of production was in place, there was really no other way for people to operate, except in a way that was consistent with Adam Smith's vision. So the work example is merely an example of how false ideas can create a circumstance that ends up making them true. It is not true that you "just can't get good help anymore." It is true that you "can't get good help anymore" when you give people work to do that is demeaning and soulless. And interestingly enough, Adam Smith -- the same guy who gave us this incredible invention of mass production, and division of labor -- understood this. He said, of people who worked in assembly lines, of men who worked in assembly lines, he says: "He generally becomes as stupid as it is possible for a human being to become." Now, notice the word here is "become." Whether he intended it or not, what Adam Smith was telling us there, is that the very shape of the institution within which people work creates people who are fitted to the demands of that institution and deprives people of the opportunity to derive the kinds of satisfactions from their work that we take for granted. The thing about science -- natural science -- is that we can spin fantastic theories about the cosmos, and have complete confidence that the cosmos is completely indifferent to our theories.
La mala tecnología desaparece. Con las ideas... las falsas ideas acerca de los seres humanos no desaparecerán si la gente cree que son ciertas. Porque si la gente cree que son ciertas, crean formas de vida e instituciones que son consistentes con estas mismas falsas ideas. Es así como la Revolución Industrial creó un sistema de fabricación del que en realidad nada se puede sacar de la jornada, excepto la paga al final del día. Porque el padre, uno de los padres, de la Revolución Industrial, Adam Smith, estaba convencido de que los seres humanos son por naturaleza flojos, y que no harían nada a menos que hicieras que valiera la pena, y la forma de hacer algo que valiera la pena era los incentivos, darles recompensas. Esa era la única razón por la que alguien haría algo. Así que creamos un sistema de fabricación consistente con esa falsa visión de la naturaleza humana. Pero una vez que este sistema de producción estaba establecido, no había en realidad ninguna otra forma de operación, excepto una que era consistente con la visión de Adam Smith. Así, el ejemplo del trabajo es meramente un ejemplo de cómo las falsas ideas pueden crear una circunstancia que acaba convirtiéndose en verdad. No es verdad, que "ya no puedan conseguir buena ayuda". Es verdad, que "ya no puedan conseguir buena ayuda", cuando le dan a la gente trabajo que es degradante y desalentador. Resulta bastante curioso que Adam Smith --el mismo tipo que nos dio este increíble invento de la producción en masa y la división del trabajo-- entendía esto. Decía de la gente que trabajaba en las líneas de ensamble, de quienes trabajaban en las líneas, decía, "En general se vuelven tan estúpidos como un ser humano lo puede ser". Noten aquí que la palabra es "vuelven". Con toda intención o no, lo que Adam Smith decía con eso es que la forma misma de la institución donde trabaja la gente, crea gente que se adapta a las demandas de esa institución y las priva de la oportunidad de lograr el tipo de satisfacciones del trabajo que damos por hecho. La cuestión acerca de la ciencia, de las ciencias naturales, es que podemos volcarnos en teorías fantásticas sobre el cosmos con la plena confianza de que el cosmos es completamente indiferente a nuestras teorías.
It's going to work the same damn way no matter what theories we have about the cosmos. But we do have to worry about the theories we have of human nature, because human nature will be changed by the theories we have that are designed to explain and help us understand human beings. The distinguished anthropologist, Clifford Geertz, said, years ago, that human beings are the "unfinished animals." And what he meant by that was that it is only human nature to have a human nature that is very much the product of the society in which people live. That human nature, that is to say our human nature, is much more created than it is discovered. We design human nature by designing the institutions within which people live and work. And so you people -- pretty much the closest I ever get to being with masters of the universe -- you people should be asking yourself a question, as you go back home to run your organizations. Just what kind of human nature do you want to help design? Thank you. (Applause) Thanks.
Funcionará de la misma maldita manera no importa qué teorías tengamos del cosmos. Pero sí deben preocuparnos las teorías que tenemos sobre la naturaleza humana porque la naturaleza humana cambiará según las teorías que tengamos, que diseñemos para explicar y entender a los seres humanos. El distinguido antropólogo Clifford Geertz, dijo hace unos años, que los seres humanos son los "animales sin terminar". Con eso quiso decir que es sólo natural del humano tener naturaleza humana, que es por mucho producto de la sociedad donde vive la gente. Esa naturaleza humana, es decir nuestra naturaleza humana, es más creación que descubrimiento. Diseñamos naturaleza humana al diseñar instituciones donde la gente habita y trabaja. Entonces Uds. gente --son por mucho lo más cercano a lo que estaré de los amos del universo-- Uds. gente deben preguntarse, cuando regresen a dirigir sus organizaciones, ¿sencillamente qué tipo de naturaleza humana quieren contribuir a diseñar? Gracias. (Aplausos)